okay let's try a problem
regarding enthalpy of combustion this
one asks the standard enthalpies of
formation for carbon dioxide liquid
water and solid glucose at 25 degrees
Celsius are negative 400 negative 300
and negative 1,300 kilojoules per mole
respectively what is the standard
enthalpy of combustion per gram of
glucose at 25 degrees Celsius so if you
need to check out some of my thermo
chemistry tutorials to help you figure
this out and when you're ready give it a try
so first things first we're talking
about the standard enthalpy of
combustion and so this must be a
combustion reaction so let's write out
the combustion reaction we're performing
combustion on glucose so let's write
this out we have glucose which we know
is c6h12o6 and that's going to be a
solid and then combustion means we're
reacting with oxygen and so we're going
to need o2 gas and then in any
combustion we're always producing carbon
dioxide and water that is always going
to be the case and we need this to be
balanced so we have six six and six for
oxygen carbon dioxide and water so this
is our combustion reaction and now we
can do thermo chemical analysis on it as
we recall the standard enthalpy change
for any reaction is going to be equal to
the sum of the standard enthalpies of
formation of the products minus the sum
of the standard enthalpies of formation
of the reactants so let's go ahead and
plug in what we know
so first starting with the products
we're looking at carbon dioxide and we
know that that is negative 400 and we're
going to have to multiply that by six
because we have a coefficient of six in
the balanced equation
then we're adding to that because this
is a sum we're adding to that negative
300 for water again times six because we
have a coefficient of six then from all
of that we're going to subtract the
enthalpies of formation of the reactants
and so we have negative 1300 for glucose
and then we're going to have zero for
oxygen because as we know for any
element this is going to be zero we
don't have heats of formation for
elements only for compounds so we're
going to do the arithmetic and we find
that the enthalpy of combustion for
glucose is negative 2900 kilojoules per
mole so this is per mole of glucose but
the question asked per gram of glucose
so we have one more calculation to do
it's very simple we just have to take
negative 2900 kilojoules per mole and
then divide that by the molar mass of
glucose which is 180 grams per mole that
way the moles cancel and we're going to
end up with kilojoules per gram and we
do the arithmetic and we get negative
sixteen point one one kilojoules per gram of glucose.